Fletcher Forum of World Affairs UP149
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Fletcher Forum of World Affairs, 1976 -- 2019; UP149.001; 1.75 Linear Feet; 1060 Digital Object(s)
  - The Fletcher Forum of World Affairs, 1989; UP149.001.00025 (Box 1)
    - The Case for Private Diplomacy, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00006; Rubin, Alan A.; The public conduct of intrastate relations often obscures the multitude of nongovernmental international contacts. These exchanges serve American national interest by fostering understanding at home and abroad. Alan Rubin suggests that greater coordination of private diplomacy, especially at the state level, will heighten American world performance. The new administration should seize the opportunity to improve private diplomatic efforts.
    - Matching US Security Interests and Capabilities in the 1990s: Challenges for President Bush, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00007; Dujomovic, Nicholas; Caught between the economic costs of overstretch and the political perils of understretch, the Bush administration will attempt to manage the contest much like its predecessors. Nicholas Dujmovic explores the options for reconciliation, but finds few prospects for immediate success.
    - Diplomacy of Accommodation: Changes in the Middle East, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00008; Abd al-Karim, Ibrahim; His Excellency Ibrahim Abd AI-Karim is Minister of Finance and the National Economy of Bahrain and has held various positions in the World Bank. He was interviewed at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy on 5 October 1988 by Glenn Grow, executive editor of the Fletcher Forum of World Affairs. The interview focused on change in political and economic diplomacy in the Middle East, and the two questions below are a summary of the round of questions in the interview. Involved in Middle East affairs for nearly two decades, H.E. Abd A1-Karim offers a first-hand look at the Arab-Israeli conflict, superpower diplomacy in the Persian/Arabian Gulf, and the effect of oil-based financing in an era of peace.
    - Going it Alone? The Course of American Diplomacy, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00009; Galbraith, Peter; Johnson, Captain William Spencer; Manger, Walter; Rieffel, Alexis; On 27 October 1988, the Fletcher Forum gathered a group of American policymakers to explore the future direction of US foreign policy. We asked: what strategic concepts should the United States espouse when conducting foreign relations with other nations? Our roundtable featured Walter Manger, currently the State Department's desk officer for the Comoros, Madagascar, Mauritius, and Tanzania, whose most recent tour was at the United Nations Political Office. Captain William Spencer Johnson, the Pentagon's deputy chief of Naval Operations for Plans, Policy, and Operations; Alexis Rieffel, an assistant to the US executive director of the International Monetary Fund; and Peter Galbraith, staff member of the US Senate Foreign Relations Committee. As moderator, Fletcher's Alan K. Henrikson lent his exhaustive knowledge of American foreign policy. Representing themselves rather than their institutions, the panelists unanimously rejected the idea of "going it alone." But a belief in American leadership suffused their remarks. An ambivalence, it seems, natural to American diplomacy.
    - The Paradox of a Neutral Ally: A Historical Overview of Iceland's Participation in NATO, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00010; Bjorgulfsdottir, Margret; Nineteen eighty-nine is the fortieth anniversary of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), and scholars worldwide are examining its evolution and success. Member states entering the alliance had differing national interests, but all held a common goal of collectively defending the West. Iceland is unique among NATO's founding members. It has never had an army. While it supported, in principle, a defense of Europe, historically, it has avoided alliances. Neutrality, coupled with maintaining a delicate domestic political balance, has presented challenges for the Icelandic government. Ms. Bjorgulfsdottir examines how Iceland, despite these factors, has become NATO's vital trans-Atlantic link, thus acquiring the paradoxical title of "neutral ally."
    - Twentieth Century Conflict in the Fourteenth Century: Intervention in Yemen, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00011; Robertson, Mark; Egyptian military intervention in North Yemen from 1962 to 1967 illustrates the selective and often creative application of codified international law (United Nations Charter, General Assembly Resolutions, Treaties, and Conventions) to justify political and military actions. Egypt initially justified its military intervention on the basis of bilateral defense agreements. Mark Robertson explains, however, how the Egyptians quickly abandoned this rationale in favor of inchoate principles of Arab unity, carefully legitimizing its "ethnic intervention" with explicit references to primary international legal norms. He concludes that Egyptian intervention in Yemen remains a precedent on the use and non-use of international law and on the legitimacy of ethnic intervention.
    - Controlling Transboundary Movements of Hazardous Waste: The Evolution of a Global Convention, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00012; Rublack, Susanne; The disposal and management of hazardous waste is one of the world's most problematic issues. Shipment of hazardous waste between OECD countries is extensive and has been going on for years. Until recently, however, little has been known about hazardous waste shipments from the industrialized North to the less developed South. Some Third World leaders point to the lack of binding international law, calling the issue "toxic terrorism" and "garbage imperialism." In this article Ms. Susanne Rublack summarizes international regulatory efforts to control such movements and traces the evolution of an upcoming UN-sponsored international convention on trans-frontier shipment of hazardous waste.
    - Software Production and Development Policy Alternatives: Brazil and Singapore, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00013; Rauenhorst, Amy M.; Accelerated growth in technology, particularly computer technology, has come to play a significant role in shaping national economic policy planning and development. As a part of this growth, the development of an indigenous software industry can provide a critical link between a country's production needs and available computer hardware. Ms. Rauenhorst presents case studies of software development policy in Brazil and Singapore- two regional technology leaders- including the influences of government ideology and foreign investment and the problems of piracy and copyright infringement. She concludes that the divergent paths followed by Brazil and Singapore vividly illustrate options available to developing countries intending to nurture such indigenous industry.
    - Book Review, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00014; Shawcross, William; Lang, James; Brown, J.F.; Elagab, Omer Yousif; Bill, James; Stevenson, Robert L.; Wu, Yuan-li; Michael, Franz; Cooper, John F.; Lee, Ta-ling; Chang, Maris Hsia; Gregor, A. James; Brands, Jr., H.W.; Lake, David A.; Farouk-Sluglett, Marion; Sluglett, Peter; Rostow, William W.; Cimbala, Steven J.; Curtis, Gerard L.; Rodman, Kenneth A.; Bertsch, Gary K.; Billings-Yun, Melanie; Lauren, Paul Gordon; Evangelista, Matthew; Bagley, Bruce M.
      Winter. The Shah's Last Ride: The Fate of an Ally. Inside Development in Latin America: A Report from the Dominican Republic, Colombia, and Brazil. Eastern Europe and Communist Rule. The Legality of Non-forcible Counter-measures in International Law. The Eagle and the Lion: The Tragedy of American-Iranian Relations. Communication, Development and the Third World: The Global Politics of Information. Human Rights in the People's Republic of China. Cold Warriors: Eisenhower's Generation and American Foreign Policy. Power, Protection, and Free Trade: International Sources of US Commercial Strategy, 1887-1939. Iraq Since 1958: From Revolution to Dictatorship. Essays on a Half-Century: Ideas, Policies, and Action. Rethinking Nuclear Strategy. The Japanese Way of Politics. Sanctity Versus Sovereignty: The United States and the Nationalization of Natural Resource Investments. Controlling East-West Trade and Technology Transfer: Power, Politics, and Policies. Decision Against War: Eisenhower and Dien Bien Phu, 1954. Power and Prejudice: The Politics and Diplomacy of Racial Discrimination. Innovation and The Arms Race: How the Soviet Union and The United States Develop New Technologies. Contadora and the Diplomacy of Peace in Central America, Volume 1: The United States, Central America, and Contadora.
    - Books received, 1989; UP149.001.00025.00015
  - The Fletcher Forum of World Affairs, 1989; UP149.001.00026 (Box 1)
    13, 2
    - Table of Contents, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00001
    - Special feature introduction, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00002
    - Political Culture and National Development, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00003; Wiarda, Howard J.
    - Development in Africa: A Cultural Perspective, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00004; Skinner, Elliott P.
    - Culture and Development: Veiled Apologetic or an Effort at Social Reconstruction of Economic and Political Change?, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00005; Gendzier, Irene
    - The "Protestant Ethic" Revisited: A Twentieth Century Look, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00006; De Long, James Bradford
    - Cultural Obstacles to Progress in the Third World - And at Home., 1989; UP149.001.00026.00007; Harrison, Lawrence E.
    - Putting the Culture Back into Development, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00008; Packard-Winkler, Mary
    - The Burma Road to Poverty: A Socio-Political Analysis, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00009; Maung, Mya
    - Television in the Chilean Plebiscite of 1988, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00010; Quilter, Peter A.; With the recent departure of Paraguay's General Alfredo Stroessner, Chile's Augusto Pinochet is the only remaining political strongman in South America. Even in Chile today, political forces are negotiating a transition to a more pluralist society. Perhaps the event most responsible for this movement is the Chilean plebiscite of October 1988. Peter Quilter takes us back to the month preceding the vote, and focuses on the role of television in a curiously restrained political environment. The story of those twenty- eight days gives us much insight into the nature of Chilean society under military rule, and importantly, what awaits it in the future. This is the story of the brief appearance of opposition advertisements on television, and the impact it had on the Chilean plebiscite.
    - Gray Market Controversies: The 1980s and Beyond, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00011; Lipner, Seth E.; Gray market goods are genuine trademarked goods, imported without the permission of the local trademark owner. These goods are manufactured by a trademark owner or authorized representative abroad and usually are similar in quality to their authorized counterparts. While much has been written about the world gray market, most articles deal in generalities, anecdotes, and doctrine, as opposed to facts about actual gray market channels. Seth E. Lipner explores what recent court cases, including a US Supreme Court decision, have revealed about the gray market business, and he discusses the international ramifications and legal issues behind those decisions.
    - Guatemalan Refugees in Mexico: International Legal Standards, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00012; Olguin, Fernando M.; It is estimated that some 200,000 Guatemalan refugees are living in Mexico. These refugees constitute only part of a swelling worldwide refugee population, many of whom are without legal protection. In Mexico the problem has become particularly acute. Fernando M. Olguin examines how the Mexican government is dealing with its Guatemalan refugees with respect to basic customary law and international legal standards. The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees is the recognized authority in refugee law and plays a major role in providing the day-to-day assistance in refugee camps, which Mr. Olguin describes in detail. The doctrines of asylum, non-refoulement, and temporary refuge are also discussed, and the article concludes by considering voluntary repatriation as a viable option.
    - Korean Reunification, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00013; Lee, Charles F.; Conventional wisdom, both Korean and non-Korean, assumes the division of this strategic peninsula to be temporary. Officially, the Korean War still has not ended but is in a state of armistice. Popular belief also accepts as true that the greatest obstacles to Korean reunification are the East-West rivalry and the balance of power in the North Pacific. Charles S. Lee, however, argues that domestic conditions in North and South Korea actually present the more serious hurdle- a hurdle unlikely to be disposed of too quickly.
    - Can America Police the World?, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00014; Rubin, Alfred P.; A Lebanese terrorist was recently convicted in a US court for hijacking a Jordanian airliner. Although the Americans on board the plane were unharmed, the FBI orchestrated an elaborate maneuver and captured the terrorist on board a Cypriot vessel in international waters. Alfred P. Rubin argues that such an extraterritorial application of US criminal law was a serious mistake, violating international law. He maintains that the international political implications of such legal maneuverings are more important than the arrest or conviction of a single terrorist
    - Book Review, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00015; Schoenbaum. Thomas J.; Strange, Susan; Theweleit, Klaus; Skidmore, Thomas E.; Ogden, Susanne; Tismaneanu, Vladimir; Wilson, Heather; Rosenstone, Robert A.; Hamilton, Nora; Friedden, Jeffrey A.; Fuller, Linda; Pastor, Manuel; Medland, William J.; Roberts, Adam; Kingsbury, Benedict; McDermott, Anthony; Harrison, Bennett; Bluestone, Barry; Jenkins, Peter; George, Alexander L.; Farley, Philip J.; Dallin, Alexander; Prestowitz Jr., Clyde V.; Moser, Caroline O.N.; Peake, Linda; Finkelstein, Lawrence; Ries, Tomas; Paterson, Thomas G.; Cioc, Mark
      Summer. Waging Peace & War: Dean Rusk in the Truman, Kennedy, and Johnson Years. States and Markets. Male Fantasies, Volume 2. Male Bodies: Psychoanalyzing the White Terror. The Politics of Military Rule in Brazil, 1964-85. China's Unresolved Issues: Politics, Development, and Culture. The Crisis of Marxist Ideology in Eastern Europe: The Poverty of Utopia. International Law and the Use of Force by National Liberation Movements. Mirror in the Shrine: American Encounters with Meiji Japan. Crisis in Central America: Regional Dynamics and the U.S. Policy in the 1980s. The Cuban Missle Crisis of 1962: Needless or Necessary. United Nations, Divided World: The UN's Role in International Relations. Egypt From Nasser to Mubarak: A Flawed Revolution. The Great U-Turn: Corporate Restructuring and the Polarizing of America. Mrs. Thatcher's Revolution: The Ending of the Socialist Era. U.S.-Soviet Security Cooperation: Achievements, Failures, Lessons. Trading Places: How We Allowed Japan to Take the Lead. Women, Human Settlements, and Housing. Politics in the United Nations System. Cold Will: The Defense of Finland. Meeting the Communist Threat: Truman to Reagan. Pax Atomica: The Nuclear Defense Debate in West Germany During the Adenauer Era
    - Books received, 1989; UP149.001.00026.00016
  - The Fletcher Forum of World Affairs, 1990; UP149.001.00027 (Box 1)
    14, 1
    - Title Page, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00001
    - Table of Contents, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00002
    - Forward, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00003
    - Marxism Enters a Confucian Realm, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00004; Shaffer, Lynda
    - The Chinese Communist Party, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00005; Bachmah, David
    - Evaluating China's Rural Policies: 1949-1989, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00006; Zweig, David
    - The Origins of the Pro-Democracy Movement, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00007; Huang, Yasheng
    - The Future of Foreign Business in China, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00008; Simon, Denis Fred
    - The International Response to the 1989 Massacre, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00009; Seymour, James D.
    - The Peoples of the People's Republic, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00010; Gladney, Dru C.
    - China's Tibetan Dilemma, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00011; Smith, Warren W.
    - INTERVIEW: Javier Perez de Cudllar, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00012
    - Playing By New Rules: Allan Gotlieb, Public Diplomacy, and the Management of Canada-US Relations, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00013; Cooper, Andrew F.
    - The Iran-Iraq War: An Analysis of the Cease-fire, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00014; Wilbur, Richard Morgan
    - Regional Political Parties in India: Akali-Dal and DMK-AIADMK, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00015; Burki, Uzma
    - Moral Dimensions of Terrorism, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00016; Jeffrey, Michael
    - Culture and Development Revisited, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00017; Harrison, Lawrence E.; Wiarda, Howard
    - The Grand Failure: The Birth and Death of Communism in the 20th Century, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00018; Brzezinksi, Zbigniew; Book Review
    - Book Review, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00019; Vogel, Ezra F.; Leighton, Marian; Campbell, Edwina S.; James, Harold; Arat, Yelim; Ispahani, Mahnaz Z.; Falk, Richard A.; Dahl, Robert; Rosenblum, Nancy L.; Keohane, Robert O.; Watson, Bruce W.; Watson, Susan M.; Pipes, Richard; Rempel, Gerhard; Jeffreys-Jones, Rhodri; Johnson, Loch K.; McNaugher, Thomas L.; Jenson, Jane; Hagen, Elizabeth; Reddy, Ceallaigh; Berger, Peter L.; Godell, Bobby; Springborg, Robert
      Winter. Step Ahead in China: Guangdong Under Reform. The Deceptive Lure of D_tente. Germany's Past and Europe's Future: The Challenges of West German Foreign Policy. A German Identity, 1770-1990. The Patriarchal Paradox: Women Politicians in Turkey. Roads and Rivals: The Political Uses of Access in the Borderlands of Asia. Revitalizing International Law. Democracy and Its Critics. Liberalism and the Moral Life. International Institutions and State Power. The Soviet Naval Threat to Europe: Military and Political Dimensions. Russia Observed: Collected Essays on Russian and Soviet History. Hitler's Children: The Hitler Youth and the SS 214. The CIA and American Democracy. America's Secret Power: The CIA in a Democratic Society. New Weapons, Old Politics: America's Procurement Muddle. Feminization of the Labor Force: Paradoxes and Promises. A Future South Africa: Visions, Strategies, and Realities. Mubarak's Egypt: Fragmentation of the Political Order.
    - Books received, 1990; UP149.001.00027.00020
  - The Fletcher Forum of World Affairs, 1990; UP149.001.00028 (Box 1)
    14, 2
    - Table of Contents, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00001
    - Forward, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00002
    - Heeding Nature's Tug: An Environmental Agenda for International Relations, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00003; Tolba, Mostafa K.
    - Scientific and International Policy Responses to Global Climate Change, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00004; Moomaw, William R.
    - Global Warming: Quo Vadis?, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00005; Solow, Andrew R.; Broadus, James M.
    - Counting the Cost: Resource Degradation in the Developing World, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00006; Panayotou, Theodore
    - Jumping on the "Ban" Wagon: Efforts to Save the African Elephant, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00007; Harland, David
    - Amazonia: In Defense of Brazil's Sovereignty, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00008; Mattos de Lemos, Haroldo
    - Traveling Toxic Trash: An Analysis of the 1989 Basel Convention, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00009; Montgomery, Mark A.
    - The Need for Eco-Justice, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00010; Kelly, Petra K.
    - Post-Cold War Global Environment and Security, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00011; Porter, Gareth
    - ESSAY: The Intifada and the Peace Process, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00012; Chomsky, Noam
    - Threat to the Republic? The Politics of Foreign Direct Investment in the United States, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00013; Felsenthal, Edward
    - The US Decision to Produce Chemical Weapons, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00014; Devine, Timothy
    - Interview, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00015; Crocker, Chester
    - Book Review, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00016; Garton Ash, Timothy; Fussell, Paul; Unterberger, Betty Miller; Seiffert, Wolfgang; Stern, Robert M.; Sachs, Jeffrey D.; Adams, William James; Wilmsen, Edwin N.; Dinstein, Yoram; McKibben, Bill; Peterson, Dale; Jervis, Robert; Seale, Patrick; Canack, William L.; Ryback, Timothy W.; Perry, Mark; Goldston, James A.; Hixson, Walter L.; Bress, Albert; Nicolaidis, Kalypso; Ambrosius, G.; Hubbard, William
      Summer. The Uses of Adversity: Essays on the Fate of Central Europe. Wartime: Understanding and Behavior in the Second World War. The United States, Revolutionary Russia, and the Rise of Czechoslovakia. Die Deutschen und Gorbatschow: Chancen fir einen Interessenausgleich. Trade and Investment Relations among the United States, Canada, and Japan. Developing Country Debt and the World Economy. Restructuring the French Economy. Land Filled with Flies. International Law at a Time of Perplexity: Essays in Honor of Shabtai Rosenne. The End of Nature. The Deluge and the Ark. The Meaning of Nuclear Revolution: Statecraft and the Prospect of Armageddon. Asad of Syria: The Struggle for the Middle East. Lost Promises: Debt, Austerity and Development in Latin America. Rock Around the Bloc: A History of Rock Music in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union. Four Stars. Shattered Hope: Guatemalan Workers and the Promise of Democracy. George F. Kennan: Cold War Iconoclast. Strategic Trends in Services: An Inquiry into the Global Services Economy. A Social and Economic History of 20th Century Europe.
    - Books received, 1990; UP149.001.00028.00017
  - The Fletcher Forum of World Affairs, 1991; UP149.001.00029
    15, 1
    - Title Page, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00001
    - Table of Contents, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00002
    - Forward, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00003
    - Human Rights and Democracy in Africa, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00004; Kuria, Gibson Kamau
    - Political Change in South Africa, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00005; O'Meara, Patrick; Winchester, N. Brian
    - Mozambique and the Politics of Economic Recovery, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00006; Bowen, Merle L.
    - A Scorecard of African Economic Reforms, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00007; Gallagher, Mark
    - The Environmental Factor in African Development, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00008; Mshindi, Thom
    - The Legacy of Communism in Eastern Europe, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00009; Djilas, Milovan; Interview
    - Perestroika in the Third World, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00010; Bugajski, Janus
    - The China-Israel Connection: New Motivations for Rapprochement, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00011; Sobin, Julian M.
    - Pol Pot's Strategy of Survival, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00012; Chindawongse, Suriya
    - Yehoshafat Harkabi and the Arab-Israeli Conflict, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00013; Berman, Mark A.
    - On The Law of Nationas, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00014; Moynihan, Daniel Patrick; Review Essay
    - Book Review, 1991; UP149.001.00029.00015; Wunsch, James S.; Olowu, Dele; Goodland, Robert; Kornai, Jinos; de Zayas, Alfred-Maurice; Denitch, Bogdan; Lakoff, Sanford; York, Herbert F.; Shafir, Gershon; Holston, James; Glass, Charles; Nye Jr., Joseph S.; Binyan, Liu; Goldblatt, Howard; Hein, Laura E.; Dodson, Michael; O'Shaughnessy, Laura Nuzzi; Davis, David Brion